Nikita Starodubcev

DOB: 03.06.1999

Personal page: quickjkee.github.io/personal-page

Email: nstarodubtsev@hse.ru GitHub: github.com/quickjkee



RESEARCH INTERESTS

Generative models in computer vision, distillation, theoretical analysis of deep learning models. I am interested in researching deep generative models to improve their efficiency and quality for practical applications such as image editing, generation, and customization.

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **N. Starodubcev**, D. Baranchuk, A. Fedorov, and A. Babenko, "Your student is better than expected: Adaptive teacher-student collaboration for text-conditional diffusion models", in *Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)*, Jun. 2024, pp. 9275–9285.
- [2] **N. Starodubcev**, M. Khoroshikh, A. Babenko, and D. Baranchuk, "Invertible consistency distillation for text-guided image editing in around 7 steps", arXiv preprint arXiv:2406.14539, 2024.
- [3] N. Starodubcev, D. Baranchuk, V. Khrulkov, and A. Babenko, "Towards real-time text-driven image manipulation with unconditional diffusion models", arXiv preprint arXiv:2304.04344, 2023.
- [4] N. Starodubcev, N. Nikitin, E. Andronova, K. Gavaza, D. Sidorenko, and A. Kalyuzhnaya, "Generative design of physical objects using modular framework", *Journal of Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence*, Q1, arXiv:2207.14621, 2022.
- [5] **N. Starodubcev**, N. Nikitin, and A. Kalyuzhnaya, "Surrogate-assisted evolutionary generative design of breakwaters using deep convolutional networks", *IEEE Congress on Evolutionary Computation (IEEE CEC)*, Oral, arXiv:2204.03400, 2022.

EXPERIENCE

Yandex Research

Nov 2022 - now

Deep Learning Researcher

 Research in diffusion models and their distilled versions for text-to-image generation and image editing

Composite Artificial Intelligence Lab, ITMO

Dec 2021 - Jun 2023

Deep Learning Researcher

- Creation and development of the generative design framework GEFEST

EDUCATION

HSE University

Jan 2024 – now

PhD student, Computer Science

- Thesis: Efficient diffusion models for computer vision problems
- Advisor: Artem Babenko

ITMO University

Sep 2021 - Jul 2023

M.S. in Computer Science, GPA: 5.0/5.0

- Thesis: Generative design of physical objects using deep learning algorithms
- Advisor: Nikolay Nikitin

Saint Petersburg State University

Sep 2017 - Jul 2021

B.S. in Computational Physics, GPA: 4.8/5.0

- Thesis: Machine learning methods for identifying quantum resonance states
- Advisor: Evgeny Yarevsky

Talks

• Evolutionary generative design of breakwaters 51st ITMO University Scientific and Educational Conference, best report	2-5 February 2022
• GEFEST: Framework for generative design of physical objects XI Congress of young scientists, St Petersburg	4-8 April 2022
• Surrogate-Assisted Evolutionary Generative Design Of Breakwaters Using Deep Convolutional Networks IEEE World Congress on Computational Intelligence, Italy	18-23 July 2022
• Generative design of two-dimensional physical objects with deep learning AIRI Conference, Russia, Sochi (Poster)	g 18-26 July 2022
• GLIDE: Towards Photorealistic Image Generation and Editing with Text-Guided Diffusion Models Research seminar of the Bayes group, HSE University, Russia	23 September 2022
• GEFEST: Framework for generative design of physical objects	23-24 November 2022

RELEVANT SKILLS

Distilled Diffusion Models

• Programming: Python, PyTorch, Docker, Git, Latex, Keras

Artificial Intelligence Journey Conference, Russia, Poster

Yandex, HSE University, Faculty of Computer Science

• Language: Russian, English (upper-intermediate)

11 November 2023